Robert H. Taylor Collection of English and American Literature, 1280s-1958 (bulk 1800s-1930s ): Finding Aid
Princeton University Library. Department of Rare Books and Special Collections.
Robert H. Taylor Collection of English and American Literature
1280s-1958
1800s-1930s
RTC01
Princeton University. Library. Dept. of Rare Books and Special Collections Manuscripts Division One Washington Road Princeton, New Jersey 08544 USA
33.7 linear feet 31 archival boxes, plus 17 boxes of artwork 7 shelves of bound manuscripts
Taylor, Robert Hill, 1908-1985
The Robert H. Taylor Collection consists of over 4,000 rare books and 3,300 manuscripts illustrating in their wide range the scope of English literature from the fourteenth century to the 1940s. This finding aid focuses on the modern manuscripts, both bound and unbound, in the collection, which is designated "RTC01" within the Manuscripts Division of the Rare Books and Special Collections Department of the Princeton University Library. However, a brief listing of the collection's Medieval and Renaissance manuscripts is included.
Robert Hill Taylor (1908-1985), Princeton University Class of 1930, amassed a distinguished collection of rare books, manuscripts, and drawings during more than 50 years of active collecting. The collection began circa 1930, and was eventually moved to Princeton in 1960 and housed in the former Princetoniana Room in Firestone Library in 1972 before being moved to the high security vault in 2012. The heart of his collection consists of the works of Anthony Trollope (Taylor's favorite author), Alexander Pope, Richard Brinsley Sheridan, George Gordon Byron, and Max Beerbohm. As Taylor himself once stated: "I felt that these were representative authors of their respective periods who could still be collected with some approach to completeness, and so I have tried to specialize in them." 1
His first gift to the Princeton University Library, made in February 1950, was the first edition of Daniel Defoe's The True-Born Englishman (1700). Starting in 1958, Taylor donated his holdings of Victorian fiction (which included numerous presentation copies of Charles Dickens, George Eliot, Thomas Hardy, and Charles Reade) to the Morris L. Parrish Collection of Victorian Novelists (C0171), along with several important Anthony Trollope items from his collection. In addition, Taylor provided the necessary funds that enabled the Library's Department of Rare Books and Special Collections to purchase a variety of special items, such as the Tollemache Chaucer, a fifteenth-century manuscript of The Canterbury Tales.
Besides his numerous and generous gifts, Taylor was an active participant in the Princeton University library community-giving lectures, selecting and assisting with Library exhibitions, and contributing scholarly articles to the Princeton University Library Chronicle. In addition, he served as the chairman of the Council of the Friends of the Library for 26 years. In 1975, Taylor was fittingly honored with the Donald F. Hyde Award of Princeton University for Distinction in Book Collection and Service to the Community of Scholars. He died in Princeton on May 5, 1985, but his legacy lives on through the distinguished and invaluable collection that bears his name and continues to grow.
1 Robert J. Wickenheiser, "Fifty Years of Collecting: The Collector and His Books" in The Princeton University Library Chronicle, Volume XXXXVIII, Numbers 2-3, Winter-Spring 1977, p. 78.
The collection consists of manuscripts, letters, and documents of numerous and varied authors and artists that span nearly five centuries of English and American literature. There is a variety of related material, such as such as artwork, illustrated albums, letterbooks, and photographs.
Authors most extensively represented include the so-called "Taylor authors"-Max Beerbohm (with numerous caricatures and drawings, correspondence and manuscripts), Alexander Pope, Richard Brinsley Sheridan; George Gordon Byron, and Anthony Trollope.
Other writers significantly represented in the collection, with regard to manuscripts and/or letters, are: the Brontë family (Anne, Charlotte, and Patrick), Charles Dickens, Thomas Hardy, Benjamin Robert Haydon, Henry James, George Bernard Shaw, Lytton Strachey, Alfred Tennyson, William Makepeace Thackeray, the Trollope family (Frances Milton, Henry Merivale, T. Adolphus, and Frances Eleanor), Oscar Wilde, and Virginia Woolf. The major artists include William Blake, Hablot Knight Browne ("Phiz"), George Cruikshank, Edward Lear, John Everett Millais, William Makepeace Thackeray, and J. M. W. Turner.
Note: A listing of Taylor Medieval and Renaissance Manuscripts (Series 4) is included as a reference for researchers, but full textual and codicological descriptions of them will eventually be published in a "Catalogue of Medieval and Renaissance Manuscripts in the Princeton University Library."
The Taylor modern manuscripts collection (RTC01) is housed in 23 archival boxes and 7 shelves (for bound and oversized items). The majority of artwork, particularly the oversized items, is stored in 17 clamshell boxes. This remains an open collection, and additions continue to be made from time to time. The collection has been arranged in the following series:
The collection is open for research.
Robert H. Taylor, Princeton Class of 1930, placed his library collection on deposit in the Princeton University Library in 1972, and bequeathed it to the Library upon his death in 1985. The Library has accepted gifts and made acquisitions of related material since that time.
"Mysteria Revelata" of John Collins was purchased with funds from the Richard M. Ludwig Endowment established by Michael Spence, Class of 1966.
Florence Emily Hardy (1881-1937) letters to Constance Innes Pocock were purchased in 2014 (AM 2014-88).
Max Beerbohm letters to Florence Kahn were purchased in 2000 (RT 2000-01).
William Shenstone epitaph by Richard Graves was purchased in 2015 (AM 2016-8).
No materials were separated during 2003 processing.
See the double issue of The Princeton University Library Chronicle devoted in its entirety to a survey of the Taylor Collection: Robert J. Wickenheiser, "The Robert H. Taylor Collection" (Vol. XXXVIII, no. 2 and 3; Winter-Spring, 1976-77), contains 13 articles by such scholars as G. E. Bentley, James Thorpe, Mary Hyde, Charles Ryskamp, E.D.H. Johnson ("Romantic, Victorian, and Edwardian: Part Two-Manuscripts, Letters, and Drawings," pp. 212-224), H. W. Liebert, Richard M. Ludwig, John V. Fleming, Earl Miner, and Thomas P. Roche. Also, the entire Winter, 1986 issue of the Princeton University Library Chronicle focuses on the Robert H. Taylor Collection.
See also: Robert H. Taylor, "Contemporary Collectors III: The Robert H. Taylor Library" in the Book Collector Vol. 3, no. 4 (Winter, 1954); "Association Copies from the Collection of Robert H. Taylor" in the Gazette of the Grolier Club [New series], (June, 1969), no. 10; and A.D. Wainwright, "Robert H. Taylor" in the Gazette of the Grolier Club [New series], (1986), no. 38.
Beerbohm, Max,Sir, 1872-1956.; Byron, George Gordon Byron,Baron, 1788-1824.; Pope, Alexander, 1688-1744.; Shaw, Bernard, 1856-1950.; Sheridan, Richard Brinsley, 1751-1816.; Strachey, Lytton, 1880-1932.; Thackeray, William Makepeace, 1811-1863.; Trollope, Anthony, 1815-1882.; Wilde, Oscar, 1854-1900.; Woolf, Virginia, 1882-1941.; American literature.; English fiction.; English literature.; English literature -- Women authors -- Sources.; Novelists, American -- 19th century -- Correspondence.; Novelists, American -- 19th century -- Manuscripts.; Novelists, American -- 20th century -- Correspondence.; Novelists, American -- 20th century -- Manuscripts.; Novelists, English -- 19th century -- Correspondence.; Novelists, English -- 19th century -- Manuscripts.; Correspondence.; Drawings.; Manuscripts.; American literature; European literature; Literature; Medieval and Renaissance manuscripts; Women's studies
- Series 1: Modern (Bound) Manuscripts, 1600-1958; 7 shelves
  Consists primarily of bound, autograph manuscripts (many of them oversized), together with additional letters, documents and drawings. A few oversize, unbound manuscripts and/or letters have been retained in their original cases.
  To avoid confusion, manuscript numbers 1-30 are reserved for the Robert Taylor Medieval and Renaissance manuscripts. Currently there are 21 assigned numbers in this series. For brief overviews of the Robert Taylor Collection see: The Robert H. Taylor Collection. Princeton University Library Chronicle, vol. 38, nos. 2 and 3 (Winter-Spring 1977). William G. Bowen, "The Robert H. Taylor Collection," Princeton University Library Chronicle, vol. 47, no. 2 (Winter 1986). pp. 119-120.
  Shelved alphabetically by author, or in some cases by title.
  - ADDISON, JOSEPH (1672-1719). "Addison Miscellany", 1715-1720; 1 volume 34 pp.
    Commonplace book written in an early 18th-century hand, containing poems by several English poets, with two engraved poems by Addison pasted down on inside wrappers.
  - Alchemical Recipe for Philosophical Mercury, or Salt of Mercury, circa 1690; AM 2016-105; 1 item 29.5 x 19.2 cm
    Recipe on 1 folio sheet for alchemist's philosophical mercury, or salt of mercury, believed to dissolve and then revivify gold to make it grow and multiply.
    Purchased 2016
  - Angler's Complete Assistant, circa 1600s; AM 2018-12; 1 item 8.6 x 15.5 cm
    List of 17 fish and where to find them, what season to fish them during, and the best time of day, depth, bait to use, etc.
    Purchased 2017
  - BAGSHAWE, ALEXANDRA. "Christmas Garland", 1946; 1 volume
    Volume of extracts from numerous authors, compiled and transcribed by Bagshawe and illustrated with pasted in pictures for the amusement of Max and Florence Beerbohm (miscellaneous foliation).
  - BARTON, WILLIAM (1597-1678). "Commonplace Book.", 1634-1674; AM 2017-75; 1 volume
    English commonplace book filled with epigrams, notes on religious counsel, conduct, rhetoric, and copies of letters received. The compiler of this manuscript appears to be translator and hymnologist William Barton, vicar of St. Martin's, Leicester, from 1656 to 1678.
    Purchased 2016.
  - BEDDOES, THOMAS LOVELL (1803-1849). "Autograph Letter to B. W. Proctor, London", 1826 March 13; 1 leaf 4 pp.
    Concerns a poem written by Beddoes.
  - BEERBOHM, MAX (1872-1956), circa 1879-1940s; 8 items
    - BEERBOHM, MAX (1872-1956). "De natura barbatulorum", circa 1890; 1 volume, 18 leaves
      Signed autograph manuscript essay with corrections and interlineations. Bound together with the printed version published in the Feb. 1896 Chap-Book.
    - BEERBOHM, MAX (1872-1956). "Drawings by HMB", 1879-1880; 1 volume, 26 leaves
      Scrapbook of pen-and-ink and pencil sketches by a young Beerbohm.
    - BEERBOHM, MAX (1872-1956). "Fenestralia", 1940s; 1 volume, 17, 5 leaves
      Autograph manuscript essay first published in "Mainly on the Air," (London: Heinemann, 1946). Together with manuscript notes (5 leaves) for an essay on watching the Parisian street scene at the Gare du Nord from a window in the hotel above the station (1928). These notes, much condensed, were used for a passage in the essay "Fenestralia."
    - BEERBOHM, MAX (1872-1956). "Further Recollections by Viscount M.O.M.", 1917 December; 1 portfolio, 4 leaves
      Autograph manuscript, signed Max Beerbohm.
    - BEERBOHM, MAX (1872-1956). "The Mirror of the Past", 1900s; 1 portfolio, 76, 12 leaves
      Incomplete autograph drafts and notes, with pencil sketches in the margins. Together with ALS entitled "A Very Brief and Arbitrary Account of a Book I am Writing, entitled ‘The Mirror of the Past’ for the Editor of The Century."
    - BEERBOHM, MAX (1872-1956). "Sonnet to Henry James", 1908; 1 volume, 2 leaves
      Autograph manuscript with corrections in the hands of Max Beerbohm and Edmund Gosse. Even numbered lines in the hand of Edmund Gosse, odd numbered lines in the hand of Max Beerbohm. Together with ANS to Evan signed "Max, from Villino Chiaro, Rapallo."
    - BEERBOHM, MAX (1872-1956). "Zuleika Dobson", circa 1898; 1 portfolio, circa 134 leaves
      Incomplete autograph manuscript draft in pencil, with pencil and pen sketches by Beerbohm. This being a rough copy of chapters 9-13 and 15-24.
    - BEERBOHM, MAX (1872-1956). "Zuleika Dobson", circa 1898; 1 portfolio, 226 leaves
      Complete autograph manuscript written in ink.
  - BERKELEY, WILLIAM (1608-1677). "The Lost Lady: Tragy-Comedy", circa 1676-1677; 1 volume, 38 leaves
    Manuscript copy, written in an unidentified hand, of the complete play. Does not include cast list and prologue.
  - BLAKEY, MARGARET (19TH CENTURY). "Agnes," or "The Triumph of Feeling", 1815; 1 volume, 153 pp.
    Original manuscript of an unpublished short romance.
  - "British Literary Autographs", 1752-1876; 1 volume, 91 leaves
    Album of autograph letters from 18th-and 19th-century literary figures, tipped in, compiler unidentified. Correspondence with Robert Burns, William Cowper, Charles Dickens, Thomas Hughes, John Keats, Charles Lamb, Percy Bysshe Shelley, Alfred Tennyson, William Makepeace Thackeray. etc.
  - BRONTË, ANNE (1820-49). "Verses by Lady Geralda", 1837 October 6; 1 volume, 28 pp.
    Signed autograph manuscript verse.
  - BRONTË, CHARLOTTE (1816-1855). "Emma", 1853; 1 volume, 10 leaves
    Autograph manuscript of portions of chapter 1 and 2.
  - BRONTË, CHARLOTTE (1816-1855). "John Henry", 1800s; 1 volume, 36 pp.
    Incomplete autograph manuscript.
  - BRONTË, CHARLOTTE (1816-1855). "Mina Laury II", 1838 January 17; 1 volume, 35 pp.
    Signed autograph manuscript.
  - BRONTË, CHARLOTTE (1816-1855). "The Violet", 1830 November 14; 1 volume, 12 pp.
  - BRONTË, EMILY (1818-1848). "All Day I Have Toiled, But Not in Pain: Five Quatrains", 1837-1839; 1 portfolio, 2 leaves
  - BRONTË, EMILY (1818-1848). "I am the Only Being Whose Doom: Six Quatrains", 1837-1839; 1 portfolio, 6 leaves
    Eleven autograph manuscript poems.
  - BRONTË, PATRICK BRANWELL (1817-1848). "And the Weary are at Rest", circa 1924; 1 volume, 4 leaves of manuscript, tipped in between p. 20 and 21
    Autograph manuscript tipped in the 1924 printed edition of And the Weary are at Rest.
  - BRONTË, PATRICK BRANWELL (1817-1848). "Autograph Manuscript", circa 1840; 1 volume, 82 pp.
    Unidentified.
  - BROWNING, ELIZABETH BARRETT (1806-1861). "Autograph Letter Signed to R.H. Horne", 1844 February 20; 1 volume, 12 pp.
    Concerns Charles Dickens, George Sand, and Victor Hugo, circa 600 words.
  - BUCKINGHAM, GEORGE VILLIERS, DUKE OF (1628-1687). "Commonplace Book", 1700s; 1 volume, 82, 26 pp.
    Transcript of the commonplace book found in the pocket of the Duke of Buckingham at the time of his death, written in an unidentified hand.
  - BURNS, ROBERT (1759-1796). "The Jolly Beggars: a Cantata", circa 1786; 1 volume, 89 lines, 4 pp.
    Autograph manuscript of an early draft.
  - BURTON, GEORGE (1717-1791). "Manuscript Poems", 1737; 1 volume, 114 pp.
    Volume of manuscript poems by Burton and his friends, with index. Most of the poetry appears to be original; much of it love poetry of a traditional kind (swans, nymphs, Chloe, etc.). Nearly all the poems are assigned to a particular author by initials, apparently by Burton as a record after the event, and the majority appear to be by Burton himself.
  - BYRON, GEORGE GORDON (1788-1824). "Autographs and Portraits of Lord Byron and His Family and Friends", dates not examined; 1 volume, 81 leaves
    Album containing autograph letters, portraits, and prints of Lord Byron, his friends, and members of his family. The collection includes autograph letters (16) by Lord Byron, Lady Byron, Admiral Byron, the Earl of Carlisle, Leigh Hunt, Thomas Moore, Lady Caroline Lamb, and others. The engravings, some color, include portraits, views, and a colored cartoon. Collected by Harry B. Smith. between 1783-1829.
  - BYRON, GEORGE GORDON (1788-1824). "Churchill's Grave", circa 1816; 1 volume, 4 pp.
    Autograph manuscript draft of a poem. Bound with a specially printed title page and text.
  - BYRON, GEORGE GORDON (1788-1824). "Darkness", circa 1816; 1 volume, 8 pp.
  - BYRON, GEORGE GORDON (1788-1824). "Hints from Horace", circa 1811; 1 volume, 52 leaves
    Autograph manuscript printer's copy with Byron's autograph corrections. Together with ALS from Seymour De Ricci to Sydney Cockerell, Paris, Aug. 7, 1939 and ALS from Byron to Mr. Cawthorn (his publisher), Newstead Abbey North, Aug. 20, 1811.
  - BYRON, GEORGE GORDON (1788-1824). "Lord and Lady Byron Letters", 1816-1872; 1 volume, 28 leaves
    Bound collection of letters from Lord Byron, Lady Byron, and Countess Guiccioli. Together with engraved portraits and clippings.
  - CATCOTT, ALEXANDER STOPFORD (1692-1749). Translations, 1716-1884; 1 volume, 233 pages
    A volume of manuscript and printed material, comprising a large collection of apparently unpublished verse and prose, mostly in English but including sections in Latin and Greek (Oxford and Bristol, from 1716 to about 1740). The first half of the book consists almost entirely of translations written in 1716-1717, but did not cease when Catcott moved to Bristol. It is clear that most of the latter half is also from his hand: this is plainly not a commonplace book, even though towards the end the compositions are mostly formal academic work in Latin and Greek, some of it by his pupils. A count of the volume's contents has identified just over 3750 lines of English poetry (and a substantial body of Latin verse too), of which the vast majority has remained unpublished. Although some of the school exercises are by his pupils, there is no reason to doubt that nearly all of the remainder of the volume is by Catcott himself, and that it contributes a substantial body of newly-identified poetry by a published early-18th century poet. 8vo (binding 200 x 125mm), pp. [viii], 129, [1] blank; [2], 130-175, 174-233. Contemporary calf, neatly rebacked in modern times with dark brown morocco, with label; edges of the leaves uncut. Spine label reads "Translations / by / A. S. Catcott / Bristol /1717 / -1738." Bound in (after p. 129): Catcott's "The Court of Love, A Vision from Chaucer." Oxford: printed at the Theater for Anthony Peisley bookseller.. ., 1717. Loose/tipped in: 4 autograph letters signed from William George of Bristol, to F. W. Cosens, 19 June to 2 August 1884, about the volume, which he borrowed for his projected "Catcott bibliography"; with one letter from Cosens to George, dated 4 August 1884. Tipped in at end: two-page section of William George's Catcott bibliography.
  - CLARENDON, EDWARD HYDE, EARL OF (1609-1674). "A Short View of the State of Ireland from the Yeare 1640 to the Yeare 1652", 1678; 1 volume, 203 pp.
    Manuscript, written in an unidentified contemporary hand. Bound with several other transcribed documents.
  - "A Collection of Choyce Poems, Lampoons, and Satyrs." Volume 1, 1673-1689; 1 item
    Manuscript collection of restoration poetry, written in two late 17th-century hands. Formerly: Restoration poetry MS 1.
  - COLLINS, JOHN. "Mysteria Revelata", 1680s; 1 item
    Late seventeenth century manuscript of the "Mysteria Revelata" [pages 23-145] of John Collins, being "A true, plaine, and impartiall Narrative, and Relation of severall matters and transactions concerning his Majesties late happie restauration, with some other circumstantiall matters, and passages precedent or consequent thereupon." This is prefaced by a verse summary [pages 1-17] headed "Certaine Memorialls and Annotations on the late Duke of Albemarle.. ." (opening "Now that the Duke’s defunct and evrie Poett.. ."). Contains authorial interpolation [page 105]. Roughly 145 pp., bound in cloth-covered boards with calf spine and corners, with the original titled upper vellum wrapper bound in. From Sir Thomas Phillipps’s library, no. 4897. Includes binder’s ticket (Bretherton, 1848) and bookplate of Devonshire historian T. N. Brushfield.
  - "A Collection of Choyce Poems, Lampoons, and Satyrs." Volume 2, 1673-1689; 1 item
    Manuscript collection of restoration poetry, written in two late 17th-century hands. Formerly: Restoration poetry MS 2.
  - "Commonplace Book", 1742-1743; 1 volume, 86 leaves
    Contains bawdy and sentimental English verse, transcriptions of epitaphs, and what appears to be original and ephemeral work.
  - "Commonplace Book of Poetry", 1600s; 1 volume, 304 leaves
    Contains restoration poetry, written in an unidentified hand. Formerly: Restoration poetry MS 3.
  - "Commonplace Book of Poetry", 1670-1704; 1 volume, 356 pp.
    Manuscript miscellany in verse and prose, principally on affairs of state and from a highly Protestant perspective, including 9 poems by Rochester, as well as apocryphal items. Written in an unidentified early 18th century hand, possibly by an Anglican cleric from Cambridge. Contains various university poems, such as (p. 200-201) "On a Whore that was whipt thro" "Cambridge, at the Cart Arse," by T.P.T. C[orpus] C[hristi] C[ollege]. Formerly: Restoration poetry MS 5.
  - "The Confessions of William-Henry Ireland: Containing the Particulars of his Fabrications of the Shakespeare Manuscripts, Together with Anecdotes and Opinions (hiterto unpublished) of Many Distinguished Persons in the Literary, Political, and Theatrical World (the Whole Truth and Nothing but the Truth)", 1805; 1 volume 304 pages
    Extra illustrated copy, made up as follows: Divisional title pages (hand lettered and decorated in color) with some titles as "Shakespeare and Ireland," Shakespeare and Fraser," "Witty Conumdrum," etc. Pages within divisions consist of large blank leaves on which are mounted columns of letter press text, prints, manuscripts, 18th- and 19th-century etchings, watercolor drawings, copper plate illustrations of Holland, pencil and pen-and-ink sketches (portraits, English and Irish buildings and landscapes, coats-of-arms, etc.) done by Samuel Ireland and others. Inserted between pages are 18th- and 19th-century signed autograph letters from members of the Ireland family, William Linley, and others, mounted on stubs. Includes an autograph manuscript poem "On Shakespeare," written by Ireland's mother and autograph manuscripts of Ireland's Shakespeare forgeries. Also includes autograph manuscript music "Edmundas Song in Vortigern," dated "Ap. 12, 1796" by William Linley and inscribed "from the composer W. Linley to his friend S. Ireland," together with ALS from Linley to W. Ireland dated "26th 96" and printed music "Cliefden's Spring," the words and music by S. Ireland. All pages have been numbered in pencil. At end, there is a printed index with page references in pencil.
  - CONRAD, JOSEPH (1857-1924). "Il Conde", circa 1920; 1 volume, 56 leaves
    Autograph manuscript.
  - Cookery and Medicine, 1650-1750; AM 2010-13; 1 volume, 70 leaves 21x16 cm Bound in contemporary green vellum, with paneled gilt covers and marbled endpapers
    Manuscript receipt book of recipes for medical and culinary concoctions, written in numerous hands over many years. A mixture of specific cures and dish recipes, the volume includes formulas for treating scurvy, worms, whooping cough, and the King's Evil, and recipes for making "Westphalia Bakon of a Legg of Porke," "Methridate Brandy," a "white soop," "syrrop of organges," and a "currant Jelly Mrs Fortry's way." With index.
  - COOLE, BENJAMIN (1664-1717). Autobiography of Benjamin Coole, circa 1700; AM 2017-45; 1 volume 317 pages 36.5 x 25.5 cm Manuscript in ink, page 285-end (but not counting endpaper) are added, on different paper and after the book was bound; in contemporary dark blue or black morocco panelled in gilt, spine in seven compartments, gilt edges; with dutch endpapers in light blue-green with gilt floral pattern.